{"tossups": [{"question": "1. Walter Kaufmann\u2019s Tragedy and Philosophy calls this play\u2019s protagonist a \u201cpassive anti-hero\u201d in contrast with the \u201cnoble hero\u201d Oedipus. Skeletal set designs were used in this play by Jo Mielziner for its premiere at the Morosco Theater. A character in this play remarks that it\u2019s bad to \u201csuffer fifty weeks a year for the sake of a two-week vacation\u201d to justify his preference for farming. Its opening describes a \u201cword-sigh\u201d that might be \u201cOh boy, oh boy\u201d from a man \u201cpast sixty years of age,\u201d as well as a (*) \u201csmall and fine\u201d melody that re-appears when a character interested in Alaskan properties enters later. This play\u2019s protagonist considers himself \u201cwell-liked,\u201d which is a reason he believes he is better than Bernard, and wants to be rich like his brother Ben. For 10 points, name this play about Willy Loman\u2019s demise by Arthur Miller.", "answer": "Death of a Salesman &lt;WA, Drama&gt;", "subcategory": "Literature American", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "2. This modern-day country is the easternmost one in which significant artifacts from the Corded Ware culture have been found. It\u2019s not Iran, but a ringed stone complex in this country called Arkaim [ar-KAH-eem] has been speculatively linked to the legendary city of Yima, who is called Jamshid in the Shahnameh. The Yamnaya culture was situated in what is now this country, which contains a \u201cforest zone\u201d that is typically given as the Urheimat [OOR-\u201dhigh\u201d-maht] of the Tocharians [to-CAR-ee-uns]. (*) Steppes in the southern part of this country are the homeland posited by the Kurgan hypothesis. A linguistic affiliation with peoples such as the Mordvins suggests that the Magyars originated in what is now this country, where the word \u201cmammoth\u201d originated from native peoples such as the Chukchi. For 10 points, name this country where the site of Bolghar is found on the Volga river.", "answer": "Russia [or Russian Federation; or Rossiyskaya Federatsiya] (the question is referring to the Siberian Forest Zone) &lt;WA, Archaeology&gt;", "category": "Geography"}, {"question": "3. This noun denotes a party led by a self-labeled \u201cconvivial cannibal from the down-coast hinterlands\u201d who created the National Unification policy to better integrate tribesmen, such as the Krahn people. That party denoted by this word sent the first delegation of African heads of state to the White House, including Edwin Barclay. This word names a party that, from the 1870s to 1980s, effectively led a one-party state, but had its dominance broken in a 1960 coup by (*) Samuel Doe. This word denotes a faction whose \u201cPatriot\u201d group opposed a leader backed heavily by Queen Caroline. It names a party that fractured into \u201cCotton\u201d and \u201cConscience\u201d factions, the latter of which formed the Free Soil Party. For 10 points, give his word that denotes a faction of anti-monarchists who opposed the Tories and a U.S. party which fractured over slavery.", "answer": "Whigs [accept True Whigs or Patriot Whigs] &lt;WA, British/Other History&gt;", "subcategory": "History American", "category": "History"}, {"question": "4. A holder of this title invited such literary figures as Plato Comicus and the epic poet Choerilus to his court, and had a man named Decamnichos be whipped for insulting a playwright\u2019s bad breath, prompting Decamnichos to lead a coup against him later. In honor of poems that he wrote for a holder of this title, Pindar\u2019s house in Thebes was spared from a sack in 335 BC. Classical accounts hold that a holder of this title offered patronage to (*) Agathon and Euripides, both of whom moved to his court and died there. This title\u2019s most famous holder was depicted by authors designated \u201cpseudo-Callisthenes\u201d in a series of popular medieval romances, as well as in Arrian\u2019s Anabasis. For 10 points, give this title held by a man tutored by Aristotle called Alexander the Great.", "answer": "king of Macedon [accept any answer indicating a ruler of Macedon; prompt on king or Greek king or equivalents] (the first clue refers to Archelaus I, patron of Euripides) &lt;WA, Authors/Bios&gt;", "subcategory": "History Classical", "category": "History"}, {"question": "5. In 1998, teacher Ruth Sherman was fired for reading a book about this feature by Carolivia Herron to her class. The cultural history of this feature is the subject of a book about its \u201cstory\u201d by Ayana Byrd and Lori Tharps. In the early 20th century, this feature was frequently manipulated into a \u201cconk.\u201d Commercializing the sales of her homemade treatments for this feature by hiring thousands of female saleswomen enabled the success of an apprentice and rival of Annie Malone; that woman was the first (*) self-made female millionaire in the U.S, Madame C. J. Walker. A way of manipulating this personal feature named for Jheri Redding was popular due to using fewer chemical relaxers. For 10 points, name this bodily feature of African-Americans that has often historically been politicized, and which may be displayed in cornrows or dreadlocks.", "answer": "hair [accept black hair or curly hair or Hair Story or Nappy Hair; accept specific hairstyles such as afros or cornrows or dreadlocks, though not all the clues necessarily apply to these] &lt;WA, US History&gt;", "subcategory": "History American", "category": "History"}, {"question": "6. After he learns to swim, a boy who grows up in this city becomes fascinated by a sunken minesweeper and later goes diving to retrieve its treasure. A novel whose first part is set in this city parodies Martin Heidegger\u2019s philosophical terminology through nonsense discourse invented by an air force cadet. To get one of his possessions repaired, a character in this city gets his mother\u2019s lover to take him to a post office to visit the janitor Koybella. A character who grows up in this city gathers the (*) uniforms of officers to put on his scarecrows. An Alsatian shepherd befriends a boy who grows up in this city named Walter Matern. After deciding that he would \u201cnever under any circumstances be a grocer\u201d at age three, a character in this city decides to stop growing up. For 10 points, name this formerly German city, the setting of a trilogy of novels by G\u00fcnter Grass.", "answer": "Danzig [or Gdansk] &lt;WA, LongFic&gt;", "subcategory": "Literature European", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "7. This non-monarch is generally credited with authoring the initial drafts of a comprehensive slavery policy called the Black Code, though he died two years before it was enacted. This man designed policies to create a \u201ccompact colony\u201d after forcing the Company of One Hundred Associates to surrender its charter. This man sent an invitation to Christiaan Huygens to help staff an academy he created, the (*) Royal Academy of Sciences. He had the charters of three existing Asia-based companies fused to create one that operated out of Pondicherry. After bringing in Flemish wool manufacturers and Italian glassmakers to help set up domestic factories, this man forbade the import of Venetian glass in 1672. For 10 points, name this mercantilist finance minister of Louis XIV.", "answer": "Jean-Baptiste Colbert &lt;WA, Continental History&gt;", "subcategory": "History European", "category": "History"}, {"question": "8. This essay reproduces a parodic passage saying \u201cLouis XIV was a very proud and self-confident man,\u201d contrasting it with the same thinker\u2019s Bergson-like articulation of a calculus that would integrate \u201cdifferential\u201d human actions. This essay considers a philosopher\u2019s remark that a losing general may play a Te Deum and declare victory as a parallel to how one author uses the battlefield to illustrate \u201cthe great illusion\u201d that individuals can \u201cunderstand and control events.\u201d This essay notes how events recorded in the letters of Joseph de Maistre are reflected in actions of characters like (*) Prince Vasily and Bolkonsky. It considers Pushkin and Dostoevsky as examples of writers who see \u201cmany things\u201d and \u201cone big thing,\u201d respectively, and argues that Leo Tolstoy belongs to neither group. A distinction by Archilochus between two animals titles, for 10 points, what Isaiah Berlin essay?", "answer": "\u201cThe Hedgehog and the Fox\u201d &lt;WA, Phil/SS&gt;", "subcategory": "Literature European", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "9. While listening to a man read this work, a character notes that it had been \u201cgiven back\u201d to him \u201cin the last stage of a desperate adventure, on a Western island.\u201d In a chapter of this work, the bleakness of a rocky landscape causes soldiers to conclude that life lacks value, allowing them to win a battle. The family of this work\u2019s author \u201ccurse the name\u201d of the monk who published it, as it is a \u201cshapeless mass of contradictory rough drafts.\u201d A scholar concludes that the word (*) \u201ctime\u201d never occurs in this work before a man visiting him asserts \u201cBut I am your friend\u201d and shoots him in the back. A story about a man named Fang is used to explain the theme of this work, whose apparently contradictory chapters are elucidated to be a temporal labyrinth by the Sinologist Stephen Albert. For 10 points, identify this incomplete novel by Ts\u2019ui Pen which titles a Jorge Luis Borges story.", "answer": "the garden of forking paths [or el jardin de senderos que se bifurcan; accept answers indicating Ts\u2019ui Pen\u2019s novel / book / etc. until \u201cTsu\u2019i Pen\u201d is read] &lt;WA, Short Fiction&gt;", "subcategory": "Literature World", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "A priest who opposed this leader\u2019s regime created an artists\u2019 colony on the Solentiname Islands. This man dictated his memoirs to Jack Cox, and titled them after his nation \u201cbetrayed.\u201d This man assumed emergency powers in his nation after an earthquake rocked his capital. Riots against this man\u2019s regime broke out after the founder of the UDEL and editor of the newspaper La Prensa was murdered. This leader was targeted by Operation Reptile while living in exile in Paraguay, during which a group of (*) Argentine Marxist revolutionaries killed him with an RPG. This man was overthrown by the FSLN, which subsequently set up the Junta of National Reconstruction. After this man\u2019s overthrow, fighting between the CIA-backed Contras and the Sandinistas broke out in his nation. For 10 points, name this dictator of Nicaragua who was in power until 1979.", "answer": "Anastasio Somoza (Debayle) &lt;EM, World History&gt;", "subcategory": "History World", "category": "History"}, {"question": "11. In a novel, a chance to play on \u201cI Love Lucy\u201d with Desi Arnaz is awarded to two boys who grow up in this place named Cesar and Nestor. A coming-of-age novel styled as a \u201cbiomythography\u201d that depicts the author\u2019s childhood in this place is titled Zami: A New Spelling of My Name. In a third novel set in this place, Dorcas has an affair with the cosmetics salesman Joe Trace. The mixed Danish ancestry of an author who worked in this place reflects the mixed ancestry of Helga Crane in her novel (*) Quicksand. Oscar Hijuelos\u2019 The Mambo Kings Play Songs of Love is set in the eastern, \u201cSpanish\u201d part of this place. Jazz by Toni Morrison is set in this place during the 1920s. For 10 points, name this neighborhood home to Nella Larsen, Claude McKay, and Langston Hughes during its namesake \u201cRenaissance.\u201d", "answer": "Harlem [accept Home to Harlem; prompt on New York or USA or Manhattan] &lt;WA, LongFic&gt;", "subcategory": "Literature American", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "12. This process titles a book that asserts a \u201cMagian\u201d culture to be the genesis of the Abrahamic and Zoroastrian faiths, as opposed to the \u201cApollonian\u201d culture of Greece, and claims to be a \u201cCopernican revolution\u201d for the conception of history as \u201cancient-medieval-modern.\u201d It\u2019s not \u201chistory,\u201d but this is the first title process of a book that is often quoted as equating history with the \u201ccrimes, follies, and misfortunes of mankind.\u201d Autumn is equated with periods of city-building in a 1918 book titled for this process by (*) Oswald Spengler, one of the two historiography books alluded to by the title of a novel about Paul Pennyfeather. It\u2019s the first title process of a 1776 book that blames Commodus for accelerating a loss of civic virtue and controversially associates its central phenomenon on Christianity. For 10 points, name this process often paired with \u201cfall,\u201d as in the title of an Edward Gibbon book.", "answer": "decline [or declinism or downfall or untergang; accept decline and fall; accept The Decline of the West or The History of the Decline and Fall of the Roman Empire] &lt;WA, Historiography&gt;", "category": "Philosophy"}, {"question": "13. The founder of this party edited the National Observer as a mouthpiece for his ideas and lost an election for governor with John Crary as his running mate. This party was revived by the founder of Wheaton College, Jonathan Blanchard. This party carried Vermont in an election in which Amos Ellmaker was its vice-presidential candidate and was formed after William Morgan was believed to be killed by drowning in the (*) Niagara River. The editor of the Albany Evening Journal, Thurlow Weed, helped found this party. One of its leaders represented the Cherokee nation in Cherokee Nation v. Georgia, served as the prosecutor in Aaron Burr\u2019s treason trial, and served as attorney general under Monroe and Adams. For 10 points, name this party that put William Wirt forward as its candidate in the 1832 election, which was named for its opposition to a secret society.", "answer": "Anti-Masonic Party &lt;EM, US History&gt;", "subcategory": "History American", "category": "History"}, {"question": "14. Two of this author\u2019s poems were submitted to Poetry magazine under the fake name \u201cJoel Michael Symington\u201d by the poet David Morton. This author\u2019s first poem, inspired by a film adaptation of A Midsummer Night\u2019s Dream, is titled \u201cThe Battle\u201d and was written at age 8. This poet drew from the death of his younger brother Richard to pen the lines \u201cOnce upon a time there were two brothers / Then there was only one: myself\u201d in his poem \u201cThe History of My Life.\u201d In another poem, this poet compares \u201cthe (*) principle that makes works of art so unlike / what the artist intended\u201d to a game of telephone. He quotes Vasari in a poem that describes \u201cthe right hand / bigger than the head, thrust at the viewer / and swerving easily away\u201d in a Parmigianino painting. For 10 points name this poet of \u201cSelf Portrait in a Convex Mirror.\u201d", "answer": "John Ashbery &lt;SB, Poetry&gt;", "subcategory": "Literature American", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "15. In his book about visiting Sakhalin Island, Anton Chekhov called this playwright a misogynist \u201cwho would like to see women enslaved\u201d and labeled him a \u201cspiritual ally\u201d of the island\u2019s native Gilyaks. In a play by this author, a man who is labeled a \u201ccharitable scoundrel\u201d leaves his house to receive the blessings of the poor in order to embellish his future obituary. Alice hopes to be murdered during her husband Edgar\u2019s saber dance in a two-part play by this author. The phrase \u201cmen are to be pitied\u201d is frequently repeated throughout a play by this author in which (*) Agnes wants to absorb the agonies of the human world before ascending to heaven. In another of his plays, Amalia reveals how Jacob Hummel murdered the milkmaid at a dinner party attended by the student, Arkenholz. For 10 points, name this playwright of A Dream Play and The Ghost Sonata.", "answer": "August Strindberg &lt;SB, Drama&gt;", "subcategory": "Literature European", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "16. Despite confiscating church lands, a ruler of this polity re-allied with the clergy in order to decrease the power of the Heresy of the Judaizers. The name \u201cGathering of the Lands\u201d is given to a process of unification accomplished by this polity through such victories as the Battle of Shelon. One of its leaders fended off two sieges by Algirdas, who attacked in support of this polity\u2019s main local rival, Tver. A ruler of this polity attempted to legitimize it as a \u201cThird Rome\u201d by marrying (*) Sophie Palaeologus, and also made a \u201cGreat Stand\u201d on the Ugra River. Despite being opposed by an alliance of Mamai, Jogaila, and Oleg II, this polity achieved a great victory at Kulikovo, thus taking the first step at removing the \u201cTatar yoke.\u201d For 10 points, name this Grand Duchy centered on a namesake city whose final ruler, Ivan the Terrible, crowned himself \u201cTsar of all the Russias.\u201d", "answer": "Grand Duchy of Moscow [or Grand Principality of Moscow; or Muscovy; prompt on Russia or Russian empire or Tsarist Russia] &lt;EM, Continental History&gt;", "subcategory": "History European", "category": "History"}, {"question": "17. This person\u2019s actions are compared to Jesus\u2019 prophecy that Peter will deny him three times in E. R. Dodds\u2019 essay on \u201cmisunderstanding\u201d a work titled for this person. In a novel, certain politicians are compared to this person because they are not criminals, but rather \u201cconvinced they had discovered the only road to paradise.\u201d Ola Rotimi adapted the tale of this person into The Gods are Not to Blame. A (*) surgeon loses his reputation after comparing Communists to this person, because they do not foresee consequences of their actions, in The Unbearable Lightness of Being. Carl Jung introduced a female analogue of a concept named for this man, and named it for Electra. Young men desire to kill their father and marry their mother in the \u201ccomplex\u201d named after, for 10 points, what Greek tragedic hero?", "answer": "Oedipus [accept Oedipus complex; accept \u201cOn Misunderstanding the Oedipus Rex\u201d] &lt;WA, Literary Legacy&gt;", "subcategory": "Literature American", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "18. Early cultural shifts in the westernmost parts of this river\u2019s basin may be indicated by the appearance of a culture defined by red ochre pottery in 3rd millenium BC, which was succeeded by the Copper Hoard culture. A coin called caltis is said to come from the port of the same name at this river\u2019s mouth, which is the furthest port named in the Periplus of the Erythraean Sea. An imperial capital along this river shaped like a parallelogram was connected by a great road to the far western frontier of Taxila. The iron-rich (*) Magadha kingdom along this river\u2019s banks gave birth to a dynasty ruled by Nanda. An imperial capital along this river was described as surrounded by a 600 foot ditch by Megasthenes. A city along this river, Pataliputra, was the capital of the Gupta Empire. For 10 points, name this river along which the city of Varanasi and the heartland of North Indian civilization lies.", "answer": "Ganges River [or Ganga River] &lt;WA, Ancient History&gt;", "subcategory": "History World", "category": "History"}, {"question": "19. This character asks his love interest to meet him on Thursdays and Sundays, or whenever she is sent to fetch water, so that he can carry the buckets for her. Despite discovering his family tree in an old Bible, this character declines to recover a silver cup from a boy who stole it. This character masters riding the beautiful, but timid, horse Goblin in order to carry out his new job delivering The Observer. He is given a cracked crucible by (*) Dove, causing him to burn his hand while making a silver teapot for John Hancock. This character, who is apprenticed to the smith Ephraim Lapham, takes up the musket of his role model Rab while fighting alongside Josiah Warren. For 10 points, name this protagonist of a young adult novel by Esther Forbes set during the American Revolution.", "answer": "Johnny Tremain [accept either underlined portion] &lt;WA, HistInLit&gt;", "subcategory": "Literature American", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "20. This character gifts a special stove to one girl because she is excluded from the rough games of the other boys at her school. In a novel, this character institutes a rule permitting pillow fights every Saturday night in exchange for the residents\u2019 proper bedtimes every other night. She dresses as Mrs. Malaprop for a New Year\u2019s Eve party and learns German from her future husband while staying at a boarding house in New York. This character owns the pet rat Scrabble and nearly lets her sister (*) drown at an ice skating rink as revenge for burning her manuscript. This character inherits the Plumfield Estate from her aunt and turns it into a school for boys. In the first novel she appears in, this character rejects Laurie\u2019s advances and marries Professor Bhaer instead. For 10 points, name this character from Little Women, the second oldest March sister.", "answer": "Josephine March [prompt on March] &lt;SB, LongFic&gt;", "subcategory": "Literature American", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "21. This book notes that women are allowed to take a new husband by custom if their husband is absent for more than twenty days in a province called Pein. The protagonists of this book visit a southern land called \u201cMangi\u201d [MAHN-gee] while travelling with the protection of a golden pass historically known as a paiza. Though this book\u2019s narrator remarked \u201cI did not tell half of what I saw, for it would not be believed\u201d on his deathbed, a common name of this book in the narrator\u2019s native tongue supposedly refers to the number of (*) lies it tells. The adventure recounted in this book, which was undertaken by the narrator at age 17 with his uncle Maffeo and father Niccol\u00f2, inspired the series of imaginary conversations in Italo Calvino\u2019s novel Invisible Cities. For 10 points, name this book recounting the travels to Khubilai Khan\u2019s court and other exotic locales by Marco Polo.", "answer": "Il Milione [or The Million or or Book of the Marvels of the World or The Travels of Marco Polo or Description of the World or Livre des Merveilles du Monde] &lt;WA, Historical Sources&gt;", "subcategory": "Literature American", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "22. It\u2019s not a human activity, but a poem titled for this phenomenon fatalistically observes how \u201cRiches or poverty, long or short life\u201d are decided by the \u201cMaker of Things\u201d before describing how the speaker can \u201close Heaven and Earth.\u201d In that poem, the speaker describes two companions named \u201cSaint\u201d and \u201cSage\u201d before noting \u201cNature and I are one.\u201d In autumn, this phenomenon is seen \u201cthrough glaze\u201d according to the poem (*) \u201cMarble Stairs Grievance.\u201d The speaker celebrates \u201cunder the flowering trees\u201d with a \u201ccup of wine\u201d in a Chinese poem titled for this natural phenomenon, which illuminates the character Pierrot in some Albert Giraud [all-BARE zhee-ROH] poems set to music by Arnold Schoenberg. For 10 points, a poem by Li Bai describes him \u201cDrinking Alone By\u201d what natural phenomenon?", "answer": "moonlight [or The Moon; or Luna; or many words that start with Yue; accept Pierrot Lunaire; prompt on light or illumination or other more general answers] &lt;WA, Poetry&gt;", "subcategory": "Literature Other", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "23. A Lenin quote made in the aftermath of the Kronstadt Soviet says \u201cHere or there with\u201d one of these objects, \u201cbut not with opposition.\u201d Activist Cesar Lopez presented a guitar inspired by the shape of these objects, the escopetarra, to the current Dalai Lama, who used the word \u201creasonable\u201d in a statement about them in Portland, Oregon. At the 1938 Sixth Plenary Congress, a leader stated that \u201cEvery Communist must grasp the truth\u201d before making a famous statement about these objects. The (*) Mosin-Nagant is an example of these objects, which are crossed with a hoe in a design based on a banner used by FRELIMO. An aphorism by Mao Zedong states that \u201cpolitical power grows out of\u201d part of one of these objects. For 10 points, name these objects that famously feature on Mozambique\u2019s flag, an example of which was designed by Mikhail Kalashnikov.", "answer": "guns [accept specific types such as rifles or assault rifles or AK-47s; accept the barrel of a gun] &lt;WA, World History&gt;", "subcategory": "History World", "category": "History"}, {"question": "24. This essay calls the Christian Science Monitor \u201ca paper more enlightened than most,\u201d referencing an article by its education editor about how children speak different languages at school than at home. This essay quotes a passage from the autobiography \u201cA Personal Record,\u201d and lambasts the conclusions from a case study by the psychologist Bernard C. Meyer. It opens the collection Hopes and Impediments and was first delivered as a lecture at the University of Massachusetts. This essay refers to Marco Polo\u2019s omission of accounts about the Great Wall to exemplify how even (*) non-xenophobic travelers can be \u201castonishingly blind,\u201d labels the Thames the \u201cvery antithesis\u201d of a certain river, and calls attention to one author\u2019s \u201cbest assaults\u201d by quoting the line \u201cMr. Kurtz \u2014 he dead.\u201d For 10 points, name this essay that attacks the racism in Joseph Conrad\u2019s Heart of Darkness, written by Chinua Achebe.", "answer": "\u201cAn Image of Africa\u201d &lt;SB, Essays/Crit&gt;", "subcategory": "Literature World", "category": "Literature"}], "bonuses": []}